right welcome everyone to the active
inference Institute uh this is week one
of uh running through cohort 7 uh we're
starting with chapter six of the
textbook this is beginning the second
half of the textbook as we know in the
first half we're covering a lot of the
fundamentals of active inference uh you
know we started with an introductory
chapter
environments looking at a lot of basic
fundamental principles behind ideas
regarding uh behavior of of you know
sentience organisms and so on we're
looking at uh neural process theories
and so how is it that neuronal
populations perhaps function in a way
that leads to different kinds of
inferential processes such that uh you
know beings kind of get around the world
they update their beliefs uh they they
make particular decisions and kind of
wait those decision amongst one another
uh they have things like attention we've
been introduced to terms like prec and
precision modulation that in the
literature gets related to the idea of
something like
neurotransmitters and and and
transmission and uh variety of other
topics that that you can you know have a
look at uh we tend to publish these
these textbook reading chapters like
these um sessions that we do and so you
can review those on on YouTube under the
active inference Institute Channel
Chanel and then uh we'll start quickly
here this is the cohort for anyone who's
uh new this is the cohort uh seven uh
page of the Koda so we use Koda is kind
of like this open uh platform and forum
for anyone who's not familiar with it um
you can like actually just go in here
and depending on like as long as you've
registered for the textbook you should
be able to like edit particular things
you can place um you know there are
Pages for for communications we have
page
that involve like you know different
equations figures that are within the
textbook for quick lookup and reference
being able to index them to like a
natural language description of what
each of them are uh which has been
incredibly helpful for people to just
like you know rather than being stuck
within a single chapter it helps to get
a a broader holistic sense of what's
going on in the textbook and then um
let's see this course yeah questions
these are are sort of like major ongoing
questions this is kind of an overview
this is not specific to any particular
cohort right and so that allows for this
kind of
nestedness of you know intercohort
communication and kind of leaving each
other uh uh in a stigmergic fashion uh
notes for one another different things
that people have been contending with in
their minds like what you know what what
is surprise minimization what are these
things like the high road and the low
road active inference that we get
introduced to in chapters 2 and three um
why are we phrasing things this way all
the way down to like deeper you know a
lot a lot of topics in this book are
kind of thought-provoking for a lot of
people it brings up a lot of questions
about what is consciousness and what is
life and you know pan psychism and all
kinds of interesting you know kind of
additional topics that we may not cover
directly in the textbook group but it it
kind of begs the question for a lot of
people some of these things so so it's a
it's a very interesting full kind of
historical archive almost of questions
about you and then sectioned into each
chapter so that way you can kind of like
see what else is you know going on in
other people's minds and thoughts so um
we also we previously were running a
math learning group I believe it's still
ongoing with um someone who go goes by
the Alias octopus but they're um you
know very smart and this has been very
useful to to a lot of people because a
lot of people are coming into to active
inference not necessarily having a
background in in mathematics they don't
necessarily have an intuitive sense of
Matrix Matrix operations or or what a
tailor series approximation is and
things like that so it's very useful to
have kind of like these sources that
perhaps kind of spring up around the
textbook without being confined to just
the textbook itself um so we have you
know plenty of other things we have some
resources regarding like telling you
about like pmdp I mentioned earlier uh
you know there's coding documentation so
it's a it's a very kind of open science
environment where it's you know it's
it's this is not a deep
hierarchical uh structure that we have
right so a lot of people contribute what
they want to contribute and they kind of
you know hope to to to get out of it
what they put into it and vice versa and
um yeah so that that's a I would say
that's a decent um introduction and then
there's also the onboarding page I'll
also mention that quickly where you can
um you know it kind of gives you
overview of what going on in Dakota and
then we can also get to like accessing
the um the textbook itself I want to
mention that um like so the the textbook
is freely available now uh as Daniel
mentioned earlier it's been around for
like nearly three years now so already
to this day like there's been an immense
amount of research that's been P
published since then um I would say that
many many many of the core principles
ideas even equations in the textbook are
still highly relevant today that's part
of the utility of continuing to go over
the textbook rather than treating it as
if it were something that's you know
already obsolete um but then that said
it's I mean for anyone who's come here
because they saw friston's pixels to
planning paper and
renormalization uh uh generative models
and and all the interesting things that
have come out much more recently that
you won't find them in this textbook you
will find many of the kind of guiding
principles that went into the design of
those models however however so once
again like you know if there should be a
central node for learning active
inference I personally would argue that
it should still be the textbook probably
um so to move on from there uh so yeah
we're looking at chapter six today um
normally I provide a very long summary
sometimes too long at the beginning of
these sessions whenever I'm the one
leading the session I'll try to keep it
a little bit shorter especially because
like in the same way that chapter one
was an introduction uh active inference
the reason why we' split things up this
way is in part because when you start
chapter 6 it's actually like this is
officially the second half of the book
in the sense of It kind of has its own
folky that it looks at so the second
half of the book is going to be much
more centered on modeling and directly
modeling uh active inference agents and
environments and and so on as opposed to
many of the like kind of natural
language descriptions of Core Concepts
so so find some in the SE second half of
the textbook so it's worth reading the
whole textbook uh whether you're
interested in cognitive modeling or
you're interested in the philosophy or
phenomenology of mind um so with I guess
I'll get into it then with chapter six
um this is a very general kind of
chapter oos to the rest of the book
maybe aside from chapter 10 which is
just a broad overview of a variety of
disciplines and how they relate to
active inference so um for anyone who's
also new to active inference actually
jumping to the end of the book chapter
10 where we suddenly get to see a
clearer picture of how variety of fields
from like psychology study of emotion
and affect to Robotics and cybernetics
and uh even economic theory all have
their own kind of interesting inter
relationships with active inference like
that's actually the the end of the book
so so uh jump there if you're you know
coming from maybe a different field and
want to see how this relates to your own
field um chapter six is a recipe for
Designing active inference models uh and
so this is really just kind of providing
you something like a recipe or a you
know the second half of the book can be
read almost like a cookbook uh in the
sense of let's decide on uh just a
couple of Exemplar models that could be
used in particular scenarios and then
from there uh what are their core
elements and then yet again from there
you can start to figure out how to adapt
them to your particular use case or
phenoma of Interest so with chapter
six um they try to boil it down to
something like a simple four-step recipe
um this it's one of the relatively
shorter chapters in the book it's like
an introduction to the second half um I
do want to point everyone out uh point
out to everyone this which is um I've
always found this rather interesting um
unlike many other approaches to
computational Neuroscience the challenge
is not to emulate a brain piece by piece
but Define the generative model that
describes the problem the brain is
trying to solve what's the problem is
appropriately formalized in terms of a
generative model the solution to the
problem emerges under active inference
with accompanying predictions about
brains and Minds um so so you can kind
of see how you know as opposed to some
sense of let's let's model some uh you
know several billion neuron uh kind of
brain model this is more about trying to
model a system uh for anyone who's who's
read the first half of the book you've
already become familiar with the notion
of a Markov blanket and so it's kind of
like can you identify a particular
system of Interest could be a person uh
it could be you know just a particular
region or or or or substrate in the
brain it could be an entire like society
and having nested marov blankets but the
idea is that the you know the marov
blanket allows us to sort of delimit the
particular thing or system that we're
trying to model and understand and so
whenever it comes to like modeling let's
say like a artificial or theoretical
person who has a brain um the idea would
be not so much that you need to model
every single facet of them you're
actually modeling just what is of
Interest what what holds well together
together what can be tested what has
different kinds of
physiological uh substrates and could be
traced back to neurobiology so we make
sure we're not running too far off into
artifice land and um and
so very typical modeling you know
concerns and problems that are found in
in data science or or or even economics
or or or machine learning like
essentially how do we how do we model
something and how do we do it in a way
that is generalizable such that it it
can extend beyond itself it's like I've
you know I've created an agent it can be
in this situation it can be in that
situation um but then also we we need it
to to hold to realism right and being
able to trace it back to the literature
and and testing refining going back and
forth um and so on so that's kind of
what chapter 6 is trying to set us up
for um we're just looking at what what
does it make sense to to model so that's
that's why I've always found this
interesting we're looking for a
generative model that in a sense
represents sort of the the mind if I
keep going with this artificial person
that we're modeling to use an example of
that then we're looking for the the
generative model that they kind of hold
uh say we Model A person who is engaging
in a behavioral task for example then
what is the model that they would be
using uh you know for that if if their
if the task is to play some kind of card
game then do we necessarily need to
Model A a variety of like other facets
of that like like um do they have to be
able to feel hungry or not or is that
not really relevant to the particular
situation that we're modeling um and and
it's there that that's what this chapter
centers around in the sense of how do we
choose uh what to include in our model
and and and starting with step one what
even it what direction should we go and
try to decide what the model should be
which system are you modeling right so
I've kind of kind of loosely already
covered uh the sense of that we see um
this may not be as simple as it seems it
rests on the identification of the
boundaries I.E marov blanket of that
system and it might be useful actually
now that I do have the coda it would be
useful to have a look real
quick this is a classic figure um you
know move the um thank you oh yeah um
sorry I'm not sure what it looks like on
my screen just the the zoom windows I
believe the vertical and the horizontal
bar yeah um AR grade out but it looks
good now thank you okay I see um
so so in this case whenever we're
modeling a system of Interest right it's
it's kind of like on the left here this
could represent our environment uh and
then on the right this could represent
our agent uh the terminology is for an
agent that's the generative model and
then for the environment it's the
generative process um I won't say that
those terms are necessarily arbitrarily
chosen but it can uh you know for some
people who are new using the word
generative very frequently it might be a
little confusing at first so I'll just
say that for the agent It's usually the
in the agent that we were interested in
modeling and in one way of phrasing it
someone else has phrased it this way I I
believe it was Mark SS who who's worked
a lot with Carl friston um
it's kind of like we're modeling a
system of interest that being our agent
or and then the environment is kind of
like the not system uh sounds very
informal or even colloquial but the
sense is is not your agent in this
situation being able to draw that kind
of defining line and then what is it
that actually allows your agent to
interface with this environment or or
survive within it uh if that's the kind
of Paradigm that you're looking at or or
to interact with it in some kind of way
and so it's it's here where the agent
commits actions that then affect the
environment it's not a direct onetoone
relationship it's kind of like we have
this sort of vicarious relationship
between the two where an agent commits
an action which is
becomes kind of metaphorically an
observation for the environment and then
the environment takes that observation
in itself then emits a new uh uh it's as
if it's acting uh but that that action
becomes an observation for the agent so
there's this kind of reciprocal process
occurring over the course of what could
be conceptualized as an action
perception Loop where an agent receives
through their sensory States and
observation uh that's perception and
then through action they they may select
an action or another term policy that
they and commit which affects the
environment and of course this can be
formalized in a very discreet bit uh you
know Loop by Loop way uh like over you
know over T time steps or over you know
T time steps within s trials or
simulations uh but but in terms of sort
of the literature and the actual the
findings we tend to view these things as
very rapid actually continuous processes
right and in terms of like a neural
process Theory so there's certainly
different ways to to look at it and then
um back to the the textbook uh other
questions what is the most appropriate
form for the generative model what what
should it be what should it look like um
we'll we'll be introduced in chapter 7
to discret State space models uh the PDP
or partially observable Markov
decision-making process is sort of one
of the uh Exemplar models for discrete
State spaces discrete State space for
some people who are unfamiliar as
opposed to it being like a continuous
we're looking at values that are not
continuously valued in the sense of like
on a range of 0 to one you could have
0.1111 one5 like not that it's uh
instead it's discrete State space so
maybe there are three colors red blue
and green um it it'd be that kind of
setting and that that's very useful
whenever it comes to thinking of
situations where maybe an agent has
discrete options you know it eats the
food it does not eat the food it moves
left or it moves right um and so on and
how do how do you set up the model so
that that's looking at things like
varying time scales have hierarchical
models and agents and so on and then how
to set up the generative process which
is essentially the environment you know
the the not agent the not system um and
and I want to briefly note that since
someone mentioned um earlier that
they're you know they're in an they're
in their own environment where they're
uh being confronted with reinforcement
learning and and how that's being
carried out to do cognitive modeling
which is certainly uh you know a fair
fair approach and it's being it's being
done and it's you know it's very
interesting it's starting to be done in
the social sciences as well which is
sort of my personal like deeper
background um and then that said uh
there's still a lot of kind of missing
um theoretical or cognitive components
to that so actually it was it was last
year that a talk that I gave where I
kind of made the case that is actually
active inference that supplies a lot of
the missing uh sort of empirical and and
and wellth thought out sort of you know
being able to trace all of these
components of a PTP actually back to the
neurobiology and being able to say what
what each of these parameters is and
then in addition to that the sort of
exploration exploitation problem in
expected free energy which kind of uh
you know the quote in the textbook is
that it gets naturally resolved or
balanced through active inference as
opposed to uh certain kinds of aspects
of reinforcement learning where
admittedly some of the approaches have
been kind of arbitrary such as oh the
agent does something random with
probability point1 uh Epsilon greedy
kind of for anyone who's familiar with
that language so so all this is to say I
I think active infer personally uh fills
in a lot of spaces that that have yet to
be really filled in or fully formalized
within the reinforcement learning
Paradigm for cognitive modeling it's
like from chapter one in active
inference it's like we already have a
very large normative framework here that
we can begin to apply and and test so
um I didn't even need to go to the
figures it's already here um I think
that we're already over halfway through
the meeting so I will start to just open
it up now um for anyone who has any kind
of questions or or thoughts or
Curiosities this is just week ones so I
don't think there's any strong
imperative to to to get too deep too
quickly
so yeah anyone who wants to speak please
go for it
or they have a certain part of the
textbook they want me to jump to and we
could look at at it together
yeah uh
uh you have a specific example for the
the first cartoon figure you you showed
the figure
6.1 um you know maybe something on hand
that's very
particular so so this is a
very yeah sure no and that's a good
question um so this is a very general
kind of notion in in active inference
actually the you know as far as the
figure goes like the caption action
perception Loop between an Adaptive
system and the environment so this this
is kind of just a way of understanding
like our agent has its own internal
states its own beliefs what it's trying
to infer um and then it uses those in in
a sense maybe used sounds a little too
um uh you know that has its own Nuance
to it but it kind of it's as if it it it
those beliefs are being used to figure
out what actions to take that's what's
represented here in the active States
and those are what influence the
environment so I mean um chapter 7 uh
after this we'll get into discret State
space models so
pdps there there's an example of like a
teenas where it's um you know it's a
very kind of classic simple experiment
where where uh there's like a mouse and
it has to navigate a t- maze meaning
there are two arms in the Maze it can go
left or it can go right and then um one
of those arms will have you know what
what we assume to be like cheese like
the essentially the reward uh that the
agent seeks or wants or prefers um and
then in the other arm will be you know
either something uh uh innocuous or
it'll be like uh like a shock or
something negative something the agent
does not want the mouse does not want
and so the the agent has to kind of
choose which way to go so what's going
on within that agent is that it begins
to model its environment uh you know in
its beliefs and so it has beliefs about
where it thinks the cheese is is it on
the left or is it on the right and as
more trials continue assuming that that
agent has different kinds of adaptive
capacities
which in reality probably yes in terms
of modeling that's kind of up to the
modeler to to do their own research on
how to to kind of evidentially back up
the assumptions they're making when they
set up their model but the that would be
the sense like the so we have the mouse
uh to the right um they they have a
belief about where the cheese is uh it's
on the left of the right so they choose
to move uh as an action left or right
and then by moving left or right that
moves them through their environment and
they get to now see the new observations
of having gone left or right and those
observations are taken in by the
sensorium of the agent uh you know could
be a visual modality so they see the
cheese or not or it could be a more uh
you know sense uh touch or or feeling
physical touch kind of modality and so
it's maybe unfortunately it's the shock
and so they feel that uh and that comes
back to the agent so so the point is
that the agent has beliefs about what's
going on they act those actions then
elicit new observations from the
environment that the agent then senses
and it updates its belief um was that
helpful yeah yeah I think so um I'm just
um so the generative model
is how the agent believes the data is
creative and the generative process is
how the data is actually
created um and uh I'm failing to be very
creative here and I apologize for maybe
this next example but um if I consider
myself as the agent maybe my beliefs are
that if I cut down on the amount of
coffee I drink per week I will get
better
sleep um the process is actually going
to be myself because I'm going to
actively cut down on the amount of
coffee I drink during the week and my
body is going to give me information
about whether I actually sleep well or
not um is that kind of it's the thing
that came to my head right now but I
wonder if that's
maybe um
okay it's a it's a really good analogy
actually I mean in the sense of you know
whenever it comes to like learning
difficult material it's often useful to
just make it familiar right like
actually make it familiar quick from the
beginning because then you can kind of
ease into the concepts and that's a
really good
example uh in the sense that you know
you you kind of have a belief or a
hypothesis let's say about what kind of
action you should take or could take to
change uh you know the observations
that'll be in elicited from your
environment uh towards something that
you prefer or want you know such as oh I
want to drink less caffeine I will be
you know healthier um and then that's
also that's a solid ins sight uh
regarding like oh my body is actually
the the process right that brings us
back to the sense of a marov blanket if
we were to model that then it's in a
sense yeah it's your own so so you know
whenever it comes to the sensorium to
having sensory receptors and this is
throughout a lot of the Neuroscience
literature this is not specific to
active a lot of this isn't specific to
active inference entirely um but in
neurosci you know you can have
interoceptive modalities where you are
sensing things from within your own body
and so as far as having a Jura of model
and beliefs it's as if like I actually
have to model my own body to to
understand the physiological symptoms or
symptoms the harsh word but signals that
uh arise from it right so so actually
that's a really good example and and I
think it's a good horis and then uh
sorry Daniel you you had your hand and
then Stephen yeah yeah two two short
comments on this first off
we see all these examples and kind of
become familiar with mapping diagrams
and graphics and formalisms and the
analytical basis of active inference to
situations so that's exactly what
chapter 6 is about giving one recipe for
how do you go from being like I care
about self-driving cars or I care about
this person in this situation or myself
in this situation to be what's an
observation what is an action what is an
internal State like that that is exactly
what happens and then also just an
important note is some people especially
more recently describe generative model
from the modeler's perspective to
reflect the total situational
understanding of all of the
probabilistic relationships in the model
that's being constructed and fewer
people use generative process nowadays
but when you get into the example and we
will then whether you call it one thing
or another in English or another
language there is a distinction between
like this is the agent's beliefs about
what happens if they hit the light
switch and then here's what actually
happens when the agent hits the light
switch so they are separate variables um
and there can be veritical or off-kilter
beliefs about consequences of actions or
What observations map to so there
separate variables it's just um no that
in more recent work generative model
sometimes is used a little bit more
totalistic whereas in the textbook it's
um used to cleanly separate the
generative model of the agent being the
total description of the agent to the
generative process which is like the
environment Niche that generates
observations and accepts the actions of
the
agent awesome thanks Daniel I just
quickly jump to this figure just to kind
of illustr St they themselves are aware
of it in the textbook it's like here is
the sort of uh here is the the
subjective model that we assume like
maybe an agent has and then that said we
are the modelers and so it's a very meta
sort of perspective but it's very
worthwhile taking into account it
relates back to what I said like oh and
machine learning data science
reinforcement learning Etc it's like we
kind of are making our own deliberate
decisions regarding how we're modeling
uh sort of the thing in the first place
so being able to maintain that sort of
Meta Meta level perspective which is
ultimately what's going to actually feed
into just producing better research and
being able to to make that level uh of
observation and comparison anyway so
Stephen yeah go for it uh yeah like just
like to nail down these Concepts if I
can from my perspective and uh using
like control of eye movements as an
example where you have a certain you
have six eye eye MUSC Muses that have to
be controlled to move the eye so the
default control of those eye muscles
would be the
subjective model is that right and uh so
like the if I'm going to um if if I have
a Target to move to a planned movement
have to move the
eyes uh send a motor signal to the eye
muscles the eye moves but if it doesn't
reach the target if there's a an error
let's say a visual
error I I don't see that represented in
the figure you showed but I'm I'm
assuming that's there's a way of there's
a obviously there are equations to
incorporate that and then the motor
command gets updated somehow uh to
compensate for
the def default signal which was
correct yes I I wanted to see if I could
find it and I I I wasn't necessarily
prepped for it for this particular
session but there are various examples
uh not many but but there are at least a
few examples of of sort of like a isod
paradigm and and recreating those kinds
of simulations um in active inference so
yeah it's kind of like so you're
modeling your your agent in this case
they have I and so so they're probably
going to have some kind of control
mechanism you know available to them
that you sort of bake into the agent and
the the model um so I'll return back to
where we
were yeah so it's kind of like you know
the agent may have their beliefs in the
sense of like maybe they have a belief
about where they should look or or if
they should look somewhere in particular
um so sorry so the the word belief I can
just replace the word
uh default
command or belief is the belief is the
state of any basian parameter especially
an internal cognitive one or a
perceptual one at a given time so like
the actuality of the
process's state that gives rise to given
visual input is the orientation of the
eye and then there's a belief that we
can say about what would I see if I were
to go there and that is where continue
on Andrew but I and I can add more about
the isage because this is a really
important key it's kind of like a dropa
situation for understanding perception
and action thank you keep going yeah
that one thanks Daniel it's it's very
helpful and uh yeah I I probably should
have clarified that so so yeah another
term is like this sense of hidden States
or or hidden latent states of the
environment uh so it's as if the the
agent is kind of modeling that in in in
their mind and so that that's where I'm
using the word beliefs um and that's how
that arises and then from there then to
active States this is kind of like these
are the sort of action affordances that
are available to the agent of what they
can do so it it's kind of like with the
agent there will be these dynamics that
you know maybe they choose to do
something and the Dynamics play out kind
of in the previous example uh that that
I think it was Joe who gave uh regarding
like oh my body is the is the
environment in this case in a certain
way it's kind of like oh well whenever I
choose to to move my eyes like actually
you know I can't change my physiology in
a in a you know click of my fingers
instead it's that I'm making decisions
that I'm subject to kind of the
environmental limitations of my eyes and
their motor Dynamics and what they're
capable of doing and how they're
connected to you know and having retin
ey and so on so so it's here in active
states that like I actually choose
something and then it you know it
happens right and that's sort of this
vicarious connection that I have with
the environment around me it's kind of
like I have beliefs I act on those
beliefs and then by acting it's moving
my eyes and from moving my eyes that
brings about new observations for me
from the environment um around
me also just to the vision example it's
um it's not a simple single layer model
so just four phenomena that are actually
incredible entry points for
understanding how our our qualia is
generated not um recognized only but
Clarity in Vision around the periphery
as well as color where the density of
receptors is
low um the absence of a blind spot and
the absence of a motor um you know
outside of just in in standard vision
and the Cade being not attended to those
are actually all very important
phenomena that so that reflect that the
primary sensory input to the
retina is not what is being experienced
as seen
so it's like both the strength and the
weakness of entering into a more complex
cognitive phenomena it has um a lot more
tangibility and like firsters
experiential nature and our familiarity
with it and yet you can you you may need
to invoke
several nested models or interacting
subsystems but that is the work of
cognitive accounting for something like
cicing it's just that like the the
simple models that don't have a
tensional modulation are not going to
capture that element of the Cade but
they can they can be layered
[Music]
in uh hello uh so I once heard Daniel
use the term UDA Loop and so I see
observation I see action uh so my my
understanding would be the Orient a
would be the generative model and the uh
decision would be the policy selection
right basically yes UDA observe Orient
decide Act is like a
procedural
parsing of this same system of
Interest here there's a simultaneous
flow happening across all the states and
there's a degree of model freedom in
which procedural order or if a
procedural order is even used to
describe it but yes observation comes in
and is recognized where it intersects
with a prior that's like observation
orientation then there's policy
inference which is like decision and
then there's action selection which is
action okay so that was a setup so my
real question is so I was thinking that
the generative model would be part of
the internal States and so would the
policy selection but it sounds like
maybe the policy selection is actually
the active
States policy inference in terms of
beliefs about policy beliefs about the
consequences of action evaluation of
policies in terms of their epistemic and
pragmatic value those are beliefs that
are internal
States action on the interface is like
the selected actual
action because it's the active State
that's exposed to the environment okay
so then would you say both the
generative model and the policy
selection are part of the uh the
internal
States as as per little earlier
generative model is used to in this
textbook to describe the blanket States
and the internal states of the agents
the generative model is the joint
distribution of sense internal and
action that describes the agent totally
that's the generative model and then
internal states are the parameters or
beliefs of whatever structure that are
not on the interface so anything that's
insulated from the environment directly
is internal States and that can include
nesting and metacognition and so on and
the blanket States composing that action
and the sense for the actual action
going out and the actual observation
getting spiked in
yeah just just kind of second Daniel I
mean for anyone who's familiar with the
sort of just programming Loops I suppose
um that would be a typical one way you
could do it is um you know often we use
the phrase action perception Loof but uh
more simulations I've seen actually do
more of a perception action Loop like
they're they the other way around so so
the agent uh I guess to put it in terms
of like an UDA Loop in a certain way
it'd be kind of like observe as the
agent receives an observation and then
Orient could be to take that information
into account to update your beliefs or
or these internal states that I stated
and then decide uh relates to policy
inference so you could you in fact you
almost should view State inference and
policy inference as kind of spe like two
distinct Pro processes both of them
involve minimizing free energy in
different ways um but uh so so to decide
in a certain sense is like oh should I
do X or Y let's back up a sec and go
back to orient well what did I just see
and then back up before that what
observation was elicited to me that that
I observed right so it's kind of like I
take it an observation I update my
beliefs in terms of internal States then
I update my my beliefs about policies or
actions uh that's kind of the decide and
then and then after that act is to
actually
carry out the the action right you could
you could theoretically have an agent
who can infer States and then after that
uses that information to infer policies
but then in the final stage they can't
act because I don't know something
happened or uh or something silly like
the modeler just left out that line of
code to to allow them to act on their
belief about action so yeah there's
State inference and there's policy
inference and there are a lot of
components within the agent that you
know they relate the two they're not
entirely um divorced processes but but
in a sense they happen
separately and I wanna I know that it's
there's a lot of conversation going on
in the chat but I could briefly speak
and Daniel has answered the questions
very well but there's a question is the
generative model modeling the prior
distribution or are we learning the
parameters like mean and variance of the
distribution uh in a sense we could say
both depending on how you set up the
model and so a lot of the kind of
General model parameters I pulled this
up earlier which can be slightly
overwhelming when you're not given any
kind of context as to what it is but
this this appears earlier in the
textbook and then it's kind of the
centerpiece of chapter 7 later um but
this is a this is sort of a PDP which uh
an architecture like this would look
very similar for a PDP in reinforcement
learning uh maybe some some particular
pieces are not shown in this diagram
that maybe sets it apart but in certain
ways it's very similar to just a
standard PDP um and so like for a um the
that's kind of like so the a matrix is
like your likelihood it's very much
related to just a general sense of
perception you take in observations and
you infer States so o
observations conditioned on variety of
different beliefs you could have right
and then B is State Transitions and
that's what adds a temporal Dimension to
these models in the sense of you now
have an agent who has a sense of what
could happen next and so that kind of
counterfactual space is now available to
them to have beliefs about oh you know
if I if if I'm hungry and then I choose
an action to eat this food then I will
no longer be hungry like that can be a
belief you hold and you could
potentially have a very high probability
of that belief as opposed to other
combinations of the the distinct States
or or factors within within that sort of
State space um C would be your pro it's
c d and and e e is left out from this
diagram aside from being present within
G um but C is your
over observations and so that's an
interesting one because it's often
framed as preferences in the sense of
this is what I want to see and so many
models in active inference are modeled
in such a way that you could learn the C
it could be updated over time by uh
updating it using uh a free energy uh
free energy minimization rule that
allows you to like kind of learn uh sort
of a hyperparameter on C so in the sense
of like oh I could learn to want
something different than what I
currently want or I could learn learn to
want an additional thing in addition to
what I already want so that's possible
or you can leave it static a lot of
people do that whenever it comes to
behavioral tasks in the sense of oh you
assume during the course of a trial
someone's not going to dramatically
change what they want in their life or
in their physiology or something so so
it can be left static so um so that's
prior D is the prior overstates so uh as
Daniel mentioned earlier like the just
the three most General components of
getting started with with constructing
just about any model are states
observations and actions once you
figured those out then it's really just
choosing what's the appropriate model to
relate those three different things and
so that's what we get in the case of a
discrete State space PDP like a relates
observation and States B relates States
temporally plus along with actions then
C is your prior over observation D prior
Over States G that's just your expected
free energy term which um you know so
that's that's using your prior beliefs
about observations and actions here to
figure out what policy to take and of
course there are breakdowns of this uh
you know functionally but uh that that's
a general s so so as opposed to getting
overwhelmed it's really everything boils
back down to what are the states
observations and actions of your model
and I have just noticed the time and and
we're nearly out so
um Daniel I don't know if you have any
kind of uh inotes or or final words you
want to throw out there or um
yeah chapter six is like the um
practical entry point chapter 1 and also
chapter 10
deal more with the theoretical aspects
of active inference but before or after
reading those if you're like how do we
actually do cognitive modeling that's
what chapter six is one attempt and one
um proposal for and the questions that
are asked in chapter six about how do
you go from a system of interest on
through procedurally constructing a
model it's there not every single nook
and cranny is there but there plus
asking in The Institute Discord and
colleagues and looking at papers and
code bases it is there so like for those
who can code or prompt generative AI or
just are getting a first pass on this
application it rounds out a lot of like
the theoretical discussions some of
which may just be perennially open but
this is it is really applicable so I
hope that um you know whether you're
going to stay at this time slot or a
different time slot or just however you
uh Jump Around the textbook and wherever
you're at in terms of like looking for
more
philosophical uh exploration to the code
implementations and actually doing
empirical inquiry um six is a good
chapter and write your questions in
theoda if you have them or email them if
you don't know where to put it or just
put it
anywhere and uh welcome to the next
phase of activity for the textbook group
and we'll have chill discussions at this
time
weekly yeah exactly great and and and go
through the prior asked questions and
some and and where you have
uncertainties you do a tremendous
service by commenting and
writing hey sorry Daniel um my apologies
for for coming late is there a a
particular section that we're focused on
each week or um what would be the best
way to prepare for next week yeah if you
look at the cohort 7 and cohort 8 live
meeting Pages it'll have like the
exact contents of each discussion so
yeah Andrew's going to it so here's
where we we're today at uh 23
UTC next week at this exact time slot
cohort 8 is going to be discussing
chapter one
and then just everyone's been added to
the calendar events and just check which
week or time but the two cohorts
alternate early and late time slots but
the two time slots stay the same every
week so seven days from now it'll be
chapter one
discussion two weeks from now at this
time slot we'll be back in cohort 7
discussing chapter 7
so um but you can you can read and and
enjoy and write questions and add
discourse to any
section so doing and contributing
anything don't be limited to what's on
the agenda but this just sets a
pace because we could we could spend two
minutes on each chapter or we could
spend two months on each chapter so it
just keeps apace rolling and gives time
zone accessibility but there's people
who don't even join the live meetings
and they're just looking to contribute
asynchronously or on their own research
so like however it looks like for you to
be learning and applying it go for it
and as Andrew said like the 22 textbook
is kind of a milestone work so it's a
good place to
ground and connecting it to specific
figures equations
quotes that gives you a shared touch
point with other people as well as
opposed to just free floating questions
which also can be critically important
it's just that they're they're sometimes
coming out of left field from other
people's
view
so that's great thank you thank
you farewell and I'll upload the
recording as well so if you ever don't
make it or you want to look at the prior
coords and times just check out the
recordings okay fair well bye